Ernst Bacon Papers
Ernst Bacon Papers
- Additions: University Archives
  - Compositions [transfer from University Archives]
    - Quiet Airs, S.U. Press & Mercury Music Corp., 1952; 1 volume (Oversize 13)
      Gentle Greeting, To Yves Tinayre
      The Devine Ship, To Frances Crane Lillie
      Of Love, To Eva Gauthier
      Eden, To Albert and Elizabeth Elkins
      The Little Stone, To Albert Frankenstein
      Fond Affection, To Giulio and Eveline Silva
      Stars, to John Edmunds
      The Heart, To Ethel Luening
      Song of Snow-White Heads, To Henry and Sidney Cowell
      The Lamb, in memory of Janet Fairbank
      To Musique, To Becalme His Fever, To Leo Eloesser
    - Ten Songs, published by Ernst Bacon, 35 Edgehill Way, San Francisco, 1928; 3 copies (Oversize 13)
      Beat! Beat! Drums! To George Fleming Houston
      Der Du von den Himmel Hist (O Thou Who in Heaven Art) To Helen Beck
      Schilflied (Nocturne) To Mary Prentice Little
      Ich liebe Dich, To Helen Beck
      Die Nachtblume, To Virginia Mandyszewski
      Was ist mir denn so wehe? To Roland Hayes
      Gebet To Sigrid Onegin
      Wanderers Nachtlied, To my Mother
      First Day, To Eugene Lombard
      Twilight, To Paul Horgan
    - Riolama, 1962; ten pieces for piano and orchestra (Oversize 13)
      I Salem
      II The Chama, N.M.
      III Creede, Colo.
      IV Nantahala, N.C.
      V Ruwenzori, Africa
      VI Gnaw-Bone, Ind.
      VII Gaspe, Ont.
      VIII Nicasio Valley, Cal.
      IX Riolama, Venez.
      X Pico Perdido, Spain
    - The Sky's The Limit, 1959; for symphonic or marching band dedicated to the Syracuse University Footballers; 2 copies (Oversize 13)
    - Symphony No. 2 set for 2 pianos by the composer, 1936; 2 copies (Oversize 14)
    - Fables for narrator and piano, 4-hand or 2 pianos (Oversize 14)
      Preface
      The Lark and the Jay
      The Possum and the Skunk
      The Secretary Bird
      The Butterfly and the Ant
      The Lion and the Sheep
      The Robin and the Gila Monster
      The Cozy Pig
      The Praying Mantis
      The Cow and the Dogs
      The Barracuda
      The Hyena and the Cricket
      Digging the Well
      Conclusion?
    - Great River: A Symphony for Narrator and Orchestra, full score (Oversize 15)
      I Preface
      I A River Created
      II The Peaks Colorado
      III Pastoral Valleys
      IV Desert and Canyon
      V Mexico Bay (The Gulf)
      VI A Pueblo Dance Prayer
      VII An Indian Death
      VIII Spanish Soldiers before Battle (New Mexico 1599)
      IX Mountain Man (Toas 1820-1830)
      XI The Honey-Eaters
      XII American Visions
    - Great River: A Symphony for Narrator and Orchestra, narrator's score (Oversize 15)
      II The Peaks
      V Mexico Bay
      VI The Pueblo Danse Prayer
      VIII Spanish Soldiers before Battle
      IX Mountain Men
      X Soldiers by Firelight (Texas 1846)
    - The Lord Star poem of Walt Whitman, cantata for mixed chorus, organ, brass, strings (Oversize 15)
    - A Tree on the Plains, music-play, piano score (Oversize 16)
      Prelude
      Lou
      Love O'Clock
      Twenty Miled
      Pop's Greeting
      Neighbor Man
      Pop's Sermon
      Heat
      The Last Train
      Interlude
      Lou's Song
      Heat of the Plains
      Tough Cookie
      Return of the Neighbors
      Tree Song
      Mom's Rebuke
      Neighbors
      Chewing Gum Island
      Neighbors (cont) and Jeremiah
      Night-Time Music
      Prelude to the Fight
      Wind Before the Rain
      The Coming of Rain
      The Idling Windmill
      Transport Plane
      Frog A Courtin
      Shirley's Tap Dance
      Hymn to Evening
      Sequel to Hymn
      Corrie's Song
      The Reverend
      Buddy's Nocturne
      Mom and Pop
      The Plains at Night (Hight)
      The Vamoose
      Hoonget
      Dawn
      Morning After the Rain
      Lou's Discourse
      Mom and Corrie
      Finale
    - Big Bend and other Stories, pieces for symphonic band (Oversize 16)
      The Rolling Year
      An Ozark Story
      Joshua Ebenezer Fry
      None But the Righteous
      Garry Owen
      Mexican Hat
      The Old Gray Goose
      The Rumptifusel
      Drip-Drop Rain
      Captain Kidd
      The Chucklehead
      Lumkin County
      The Buffalo Skinners
      Weary Hut
      The Big Bend
    - "Peterborough, N.H.", 1952; suite for viola and piano, for Mrs. Edward MacDowell (Oversize 16)
      The Farm
      The 11:38 Daily
      The Rill
      Monadnock at Dusk
      Glad Day
    - Three Pieces for Brass Choir and Percussion, 1 volumes (Oversize 17)
      The Rolling Years
      The Little Black Train
      Granite Boys
    - August (poem by Annette Wynne) (Oversize 17)
    - Adam and Eve (Oversize 17)
    - After the Rain (Oversize 17)
    - Ariel's Song (Oversize 17)
    - Precepts of Angelus Silesius, for 2 or 3-part women's choir, for Bennington College (Oversize 17)
    - The Bohemian Hymn, for mixed voices, accompanied (Oversize 17)
    - Boston Hymn, chorale for mixed voices, a capella or accompanied (Oversize 17)
    - Apothegms, for mixed chorus and accompaniment (Oversize 17)
      The Eternal Paradox
      The Lasting Stone
      Definition
      The Passing Moment
      Uses of Wit
      Eternity
      Truth and Man
      Nature
      The Poet
      Pedantry
      Spirits and Elements
      Teaching
      The Happier Sheep
      Gifts from the Devil
      The Levellers
      The Camel
      Our Friends
      To a Loving Husband
    - Pieces For Band (Oversize 17)
      The Sky's the Limit
    - Symphony No. 2, 1936 (Oversize 18)
    - Buffalo Gals: Songs from the American Folk for Voice and Piano, Carl Fischer Inc., NY, 1966 (Oversize 18)
    - Four Pieces for Wind Solo and Piano (Oversize 18)
      Dusk Over the Marsh
      Stony-Lonesome
      4 Poultry or The Barnyard
      Pecos Bill
    - Four Pieces for Two Violins and Piano (Oversize 18)
      Ode to Dusk
      Ground Hog
      Three Little Babes
    - Pieces for Solo Piano (Oversize 18)
      Lost Children
      Stoney-Lonesome (Ind.)
      The White Window
      Little Things
      A Western Habanera
      Reuben
      Flop-Eared Man
      The Cool Moon (a nocturne)
      Hell in Texas (revised)
      The Ragged Rascal
      Petticoat Slide
      The Lobo Girl of Devil's River
    - Five Apothegms of Lao-Tzu, Bynner translation, for narrator and string quartet (Oversize 19)
      The Breath of Life
      Those Who Would Take Over
      A Man's Heart
      The Yield of Water
      Renewal
    - Music for Cello and Piano (Oversize 19)
      The Flower of Night
      The Purple Land
      The Rose of Wintertime (Christmas carol)
      Greensleeves (Christmas carol)
      Mother and Child (Christmas carol)
      The Holly and the Ivy (Christmas carol)
    - Welcome, suite for cello and piano, written for the birth of Bacon's son Paul (Oversize 19)
      Birth
      Light
      Love (a mother and father regard their child)
    - The Barnyard, 2 copies (Oversize 19)
    - Prologue to "Everyman", 1945; for organ, solo cello and optional harp; written for the Rocky Mountain Festival, Denver University (Oversize 19)
    - The Dove (Oversize 19)
      I The Dove
      II The Vulture
      III The Sparrow
      IV The Pigeon
      V The Condor
    - Quintet for Strings and Piano, based on The Tempest; full score and parts for cello, violin, viola, and violin (Oversize 20)
      Shipwreck and the Enchanted Isle
      Ariel
      Conspirators
      Caliban
      Miranda and Prospero
      Danse of the Shapes
      Diverse Spirits Punish the Conspirators and Prospero's Epilogue
    - By Blue Ontario's Shore (Oversize 21)
    - Caliban, includes untitled fragment; 2 folders (Oversize 20)
    - The Colorado Trail (Oversize 20)
    - Calm Soul (Oversize 20)
    - A Carol (Oversize 20)
    - Courting Day / Monday Was My Courting Day (Oversize 20)
    - A Cradle Hymn (Oversize 21)
    - Cripple Creek (Oversize 21)
    - Destiny of the Flag (Oversize 21)
    - Definition (Oversize 21)
    - Death (Oversize 21)
    - Day's End (Oversize 21)
    - The Cruel Ship's Carpenter (Oversize 21)
    - Ecclesiastes
      - Full score, for mixed chorus and orchestra with bass and soprano solos; no title songs; 2 folders (Oversize 22)
      - Piano score (Oversize 22)
    - Flowers and Moonlight (Oversize 21)
    - The Floundering Whale (Oversize 21)
    - The First Sunset (Oversize 21)
    - Eternity (Oversize 21)
    - The Eternal Goodness (Oversize 21)
    - Epitaph (Oversize 21)
    - From Emily's Diary, full score; for women's chorus and orchestra (small) (Oversize 23)
    - Songs for High Voice, poem of Emily Dickinson (Oversize 23)
      Sweet is the Swamp
      Ample Make this Bed
      A Word
      The Gentlest Mother
      I'm Nobody
      As Imperceptibly as Grief
      The Sun Went Down
      Savior
      Snow
      A Cemetery
      The Mountain
      Yellow
      The Pedigree of Honey
      As I Love Thee
      She Went
      A Threadless Way
      With the First Arbutus
      This Wondrous Sea
      It's Such a Little Thing
      A Spider
      The Morns are Meeker
      Water
      To Venerate the Days
      Few Get Enough
    - Yes I Do (Oversize 22)
    - The School Boy (Oversize 22)
    - St. James's Hospital (Oversize 22)
    - Sailing Homeward (Oversize 22)
    - The Poet (Oversize 22)
    - The Passing Moment (Oversize 23)
    - Wastin' Time (Oversize 23)
    - The Unseen Soul (Oversize 23)
    - The Spanish Armada (Oversize 23)
    - The Source (Oversize 23)
    - Night and Day (Oversize 23)
    - In the Valley (Oversize 23)
    - The Day of Old Rameses (Oversize 23)
    - I Felt a Funeral in My Brain (Oversize 23)
    - Homecoming (Oversize 23)
    - Hammar Man (Oversize 23)
  - Writings [transfer from University Archives]
    This material transferred from University Archives, 1991.
    - Manuscripts
      - The Art of Giving [alternate title: The case for patronage], typescript; 3 copies (Box 7)
      - The Critic's Dilemma, typescript; 2 copies (Box 7)
      - Der Herr Diktator, typescript; 2 copies (Box 7)
      - The Doctoral Complot, typescript; 2 copies (Box 7)
      - The Farmer's Museum, 2 copies (Box 7)
      - "Musical Quillets" in Music Journal, July, 1966; 2 copies (Box 7)
      - Music and Children, typescript; 2 copies (Box 7)
      - A Music Center, typescript; 2 copies (Box 7)
      - The New Puritanism, typescript; 2 copies (Box 7)
      - Retirement by the Clock, typescript, typescript copy; 2 copies (Box 7)
      - Fables, typescript copy; 106 pages (Box 7)
  - Artwork [transfer from University Archives]
    - Drawings, 3 items (Box 7)
    - Paintings, 3 items (Box 7)
    - Watercolors (Oversize 24)
  - Compositions [transfer from University Archives]
    - Air des Bouffons, score (Oversize 24)
    - Animals' Christmas Oratorio, for boys or women's voices with narrator & piano; includes published edition, Theodore Presser, Bryn Mawr, PA; 2 copies (Oversize 24)
    - Bearwalla, orchestral score (Oversize 30)
    - Beat! Beat! Drums!, score; with obbligato voice (Oversize 24)
    - Billy in the Darbies, Melville's poem in "Billy Budd" (Box 5)
    - Canons a capella (Oversize 24)
    - Canons on names (Box 7)
    - Canons, vocal, 3 items (Box 10)
    - Cello ensembles, easy (Box 7)
    - Chittenango, orchestral parts (Box 5)
    - Choral parts for canons / Vocal duets (Box 7)
    - Chorus with piano (Box 9)
    - Chorus V / Christmas Chous (Oversize 24)
      Babe of Bethlehem (2 versions)
      Children, Go (2 versions)
      Christmas Eve
      The Friendly Beasts
      Go Tell It On the Mountain
      The Infant Jesus
      King Wenceslas
      Mary
      Masters in the Hall (2 versions)
      Sussex Carol (2 versions)
      The Valley of Judea
      Wassail Song
      Ye Shepherds
      Year's End
    - Concerto Grosso (Oversize 24)
    - The Corn Belt for Band (Oversize 24)
    - Drum Taps (full score) (Oversize 24)
    - Duets (simple) (Box 5)
    - Early German songs, 1 volume (Oversize 24)
    - Emily Dickinson originals from "Nature" (Oversize 24)
    - E[mily] Dickinson originals # II (Oversize 24)
    - E[mily] Dickinson settings with orchestra (Oversize 25)
    - E[mily] Dickinson song (last, complete) (Oversize 25)
    - Emily Dickinson songs / 1 Robert Burns song (Oversize 25)
    - Emily's Diary - S & A chorus with small orchestra (Oversize 25)
    - Folk settings, two versions, one with piano (simple, unison), the other for solo or unison chorus (Oversize 25)
    - "Hootnanny," a collection of 4-hand piano pieces (Oversize 25)
    - Housman, A. E. (songs to) (Oversize 25)
    - Housman, A. E. (songs to) (Box 9)
    - Hymns, 2 items (Box 8)
    - Hymns & anthems, 35 items (Oversize 25)
    - Hymns for chorus and strings [missing 2/8/2017], 5 items
    - Jehovah & the Ark, 2 piano version, originals; includes Interludes (Oversize 25)
    - Lieder MSS. published or changed (earlier versions) (Oversize 26)
    - "The Lord Star" cantata for mixed chorus, baritone, organ & wind (Box 9)
    - Music notebooks (Box 9)
      Cello Concerto; Folk Songs; Fugue; Piano Pieces; Scherzo
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - My River, parts & score (Oversize 26)
    - "Nature", includes bound photocopy of published edition, E. C. Schirmer, Boston, MA; 2 copies (Oversize 30)
    - Non-Dickinson lieder (Oversize 26)
    - Notes on Babylon (Box 8)
    - "Of a Feather", for SA chorus with piano (Oversize 26)
    - Patriotic American songs, etc., 10 items (Oversize 26)
    - Piano (children, easy) (Oversize 26)
    - Piano, four-hand and three-hand for 2 pianos (Oversize 27)
    - Piano, mostly published, includes published edition of "The Hootnanny for One or Two Pianos - Four Hands," Chappell, N.Y. (Oversize 26)
    - Piano (Parliament of Fowls) (Box 8)
    - Piano originals (Oversize 30)
    - Piano pieces, Grades 1 to 6 (Oversize 30)
    - Piano pieces, miscellaneous, 2 folders (Oversize 27)
    - Piano pieces, miscellaneous, solo, 2 folders (Oversize 27)
    - Piano pieces needing revise or re-write (Oversize 26)
    - Piano solo [missing 2/8/2017]
    - Piano solo, Beginner I (Oversize 28)
    - Piano solo, Simple Airs from Here and There (Oversize 28)
    - Piano solos vocal solos / Progressive versions of 3 tender songs (late) (Oversize 29)
    - Piano works (late) (Box 9)
    - Piano works (very late) (Oversize 29)
    - Pianos (2) [missing 2/8/2017], 2 folders
    - The Possum and the Skunk (Box 9)
    - Publisher's engravings of: "Year's End," "Go, Tell it on the Mountain," "Far Away" (Box 8)
    - Recessional, includes various fragments (Box 8)
    - Remembering Ansel Adams (Oversize 29)
    - Rounds and canons [missing 2/8/2017]
    - SA a capella [missing 2/8/2017]
    - SA with piano or TB (Oversize 28)
    - SATB a capella (Oversize 28)
    - SATB with piano [missing 2/8/2017]
    - Sketches [missing 2/8/2017]
    - Sketches for Requiem (Box 9)
    - Sonata for cello and piano (Oversize 32)
    - Sonata for viola and piano [missing 2/8/2017]
    - Sonatina et al. "No. 7" (Box 8)
    - Songs (group) [missing 2/8/2017]
    - Trio piano, violin, cello, first version (Box 8)
    - Trio, score (Box 8)
    - Trio, #2, copy of score and parts (Box 8)
    - Unison chorus with piano (Oversize 28)
    - Viola and piano sonata (Box 8)
    - Voyage to Ararat (Oversize 32)
    - White Marsh (Box 9)
    - Wind ensembles with piano and narrator, 2 items (Oversize 32)
    - Woodpile (Oversize 29)
    - Woodpile of incomplete very late works, 2 folders (Oversize 29)
    - Miscellaneous musical sketches, fragments (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous original pages for voice and piano (Oversize 31)
    - Untitled songbook (Oversize 31)
  - Writings [transfer from University Archives]
    - Drama
      - "The Whitehouse Blues" script (Box 9)
    - Essays
      - "Advice to Music Patrons", manuscript (Box 9)
      - "The Artist and the Critic" in "Twenty Articles on the Art of Criticism," Northwest Arts, 1984; reprint (Box 9)
      - "Author's Note", manuscript draft (Box 9)
      - "Means and Extremes," The Provincial Musician, April 1937 (Box 9)
      - "Poetry in Search of Music"; "Songs of Ernst Bacon" / J. St. Edmunds, The Sewanee Review, 1941 (Box 9)
      - "Retirement by the Calendar", manuscript draft (Box 9)
      - "Revolt and Change", manuscript draft; 3 copies (Box 9)
      - "Toward a Musical Home-Rule," Southern Literary Messenger, photocopy of article (Box 9)
      - "The Tragedy of American Music", manuscript draft (Box 9)
    - Poetry
      - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Speeches
      - "Remarks to the Music Faculty", 1957; typescript (Box 9)
    - Miscellany
      - Apothegms, typescripts, carbons (Box 9)
      - Autobiography, original plan and outline; includes 1987 article "Native soil" from Living Music, vol. 5 no. 2 Winter 1987 (Box 10)
      - Autobiography, original draft; handwritten (Box 10)
      - Autobiography, original draft; additional material, handwritten; 103 pages (Box 10)
      - Autobiography, additional material; handwritten and typescript; 47 pages (Box 10)
      - Autobiography, miscellaneous autobiographical material, handwritten and typescript; 47 pages (Box 10)
      - Autobiography, first version; handwritten; 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Autobiography, "Friends, depression years"; handwritten (Box 11)
      - Autobiography, introduction; heavily revised (and rejected) version; typescript with handwritten corrections (Box 11)
      - Autobiography, first typed draft; typescript with edits; 5 folders (Box 11)
      - Autobiography, miscellaneous pages; typescript; 141 pages (Box 12)
      - Autobiography, miscellaneous pages; typescript; 182 pages (Box 12)
      - Autobiography, miscellaneous pages; typescript; 55 pages (Box 12)
      - Autobiography, "O. N. Cable" version; typescript (Box 12)
      - Autobiography, spiral-bound typescript with handwritten corrections (Box 12)
      - Autobiography, miscellaneous unsorted material; typescript; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - [The Honor of Music] The Pathology of Music [earlier title], typescript with corrections (Box 13)
      - The Honor of Music, draft, draft with corrections; 1 folder (Box 13)
      - The Honor of Music, draft (cont.), typescript with corrections; 6 folders (Box 14)
      - The Honor of Music, draft (cont.), typescript with corrections; 1 folder (Box 15)
      - The Honor of Music, bound, typescript, spiral bound with handwritten forward (Box 15)
      - "Imaginary Dialogues", typescript (Box 15)
      - Special items, manuscript drafts (Box 15)
      - "Tales from the Music World", manuscript drafts; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Memorabilia [transfer from University Archives]
    - Awards, 1952; Campion Society Citation (Box 8)
    - Photographs (Box 15)
    - Photographs, includres clipping of Bacon when he was artist in residence at Syracuse University (Oversize 31)
    - Printed material
      - "Ernst Bacon: A Contemporary Tribute" by Paul Horgan (Box 15)
      - "Remembering Ernst Bacon", 1990; program honoring his life (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
    - Student career, notebook, score sheets (Box 15)
- Additions: Don Siebert
  This material gift of Don Siebert, 1993.
  - Scores
    - Early Compositions for Piano, original piano score, bound (Oversize 32)
    - Early Songs, original piano score, bound (Oversize 7)
    - Five Apothegms of Lao-Tzu, (unbound), Bynner translation for narrator and string quartet; scores for violin I, violin II, viola, cello and narrator (Oversize 31)
    - Five Hymns, Summy-Birchard Publishin Co., Evanston, IL, 1952; for mixed chorus and piano or organ; published as part of Birchard Boston University Contemporary Music series (Box 15)
    - Five Hymns for chorus and strings, for mixed chorus and piano or organ (Oversize 32)
    - Folk Songs, original piano score, bound (Oversize 31)
    - The Robe, Shawnee Press, Delaware Water Gap, PA, 1953; for mixed chorus and piano; published as part of Waring Workshop series (Box 15)
    - Shouting Pilgrim, Lawson-Gould Music Publishers, NY, 1954; a fuguing tune for mixed chorus and piano four hands; published as part of Robert Shaw Choral series (Box 15)
  - Writings
    - Essay, Life and Freedom, typescript (Box 15)